Finding Aid for Arthur Rich Papers 1962-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur Rich Papers
1962-1989
Rich, Arthur, 1937-1990.
University of Michigan physicist specializing in precision measurements of atomic physics; best known for working with positrons and positronium. Correspondence, grant proposals, course material, articles, clippings and photographs pertaining to Rich's research, teaching and administrative duties as a physics professor at the University of Michigan. Some materials relate to his colleague, William L. Williams.
955 Aa 2
6.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Paula Rich (donor 8237 ) in February 1994.
The collection is open for research, except where indicated.
Physicist Arthur Rich was internationally recognized for his contributions to the field of precision measurements of atomic physics, particularly for his work on positrons, the antimatter equivalent of the electron.
Born in New York City on August 30, 1937, Rich joined the University of Michigan physics faculty in 1966, after completing his Bachelor of Science degree at Brooklyn College in 1959, his Master's degree at Columbia University in 1961, and his Ph.D. at Michigan in 1965. His thesis research under H. Richard Crane involved measurements of the magnetic moment (g-2 factor) of the positron. These experiments continued until 1980 and included measurements of the electron and proton g-factor.
Rich went on to carry out a series of experiments on the lifetime of ortho-positronium, which revealed the only known experimental discrepancy with the theory of quantum electrodynamics. By the 1980s, Rich was doing highly innovative work in developing techniques for polarizing beams of positrons; in 1988, with James Van House, he co-invented the positron microscope. Toward the end of his life, Rich was working on an international collaboration to fabricate anti-hydrogen, which would be the first anti-matter element.
Rich's interests were not limited to atomic physics. He was keenly interested in astrophysics, and during the 1970s he carried out research at the Cerro Tololo, Chile telescope. He also displayed a strong commitment to undergraduate education, often including undergraduates as an integral part of his research teams.
Rich was a senior fellow of the Michigan Society of Fellows and of the American Physical Society, and was a member of the New York Academy of Sciences. He died on August 25, 1990.
The Arthur Rich Papers span the years 1962 to 1989, and document diverse aspects of his career as a professor of physics at the University of Michigan. The collection has been divided into seven series: Biographical Information, Research Activities, Course Materials, Correspondence, Publications, Topical Files, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Astrophysics.; Physicists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Physics.; Positrons.; Rich, Arthur, 1937-1990.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; Williams, W. L. (William Lee), 1937-
Subjects - Visual Material:
Cerro Tololo Inter-American Observatory.; Laboratories--Furniture, equipment, etc.; Laboratories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Rich, Arthur, 1937-1990.; Scientific equipment.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; Williams, W. L. (William Lee), 1937-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical Information
  Biographical Information (2 folders, 1 printed volume; 1978-1991) contains Rich's curriculum vita and faculty evaluations. The latter are Rich's annual summaries of his research activities and other accomplishments, which were submitted to the Chair and Executive Committee of the Physics Department. The series also contains the published proceedings of the Arthur Rich Memorial Symposium, which was held in May 1991.
  - Biographical Material on Rich, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Evaluations, 1978-1989 (Box 1)
  - Time Reversal-The Arthur Rich Memorial Symposium, edited by M. Skalsey, P.H. Bucksbaum, et al., 1991 (Box 1)
- Research Activities
  Research Activities (2 linear ft.; 1970-1989) primarily consists of grant proposals, which document the planning, progress, staffing, and funding of research projects. Whenever possible, projects are listed by the title Rich gave them; otherwise, a general topic or funding agency name is used. There are also a few folders which contain research-related calculations and notes.
  - Anti-Hydrogen Project, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - "Applications of Intense Positron Beams", lecture at Columbia, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Astrophysics calculations and observations, circa 1975 (Box 1)
  - Astrophysics Correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Astrophysics notes, 1973-1978 (Box 1)
  - Astrophysics Research Funding, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - "Bio-chirality Search with Variable Helicity Positrons" Grant Proposal, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
  - "Circular Polarization of Optical Radiation from Astronomical Sources" Grant Proposal, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Electron g-factor Anomaly Grant Proposals, 1973-1980; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "First Results of a Positron Microscope" revisions, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - "Fundamental Investigations Using Positrons and Positronium" proposal, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Gamma Ray Telescope (GARTAR) calculations, circa 1970 (Box 1)
  - Gamma Ray Telescope (GARTAR) proposal to NASA, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Idaho National Engineering Laboratory Positron Research Proposal, 1989 (Box 1)
  - "Investigations of Lepton Interactions" Grant Renewal, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "Investigations of Low Energy Lepton Interactions technical report, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Lepton Interaction Grant Proposals, 1980-1988; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "Low Energy Lepton Interactions", 1983-1988 (Box 2)
  - NASA correspondence and proposal, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
  - NASA Space Propulsion Center proposal, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - National Bureau of Standards Precision Measurement Grants, 1980 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation Grant Requests, 1974-1981 (Box 2)
  - Paul, Derek A.L. (University of Toronto collaboration), 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Photon Calculations, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Polarimeter Drawings, circa 1987 (Box 2)
  - Polarimeter Instrumental Calculations, circa 1970 (Box 2)
  - Positron Emission Tomography (PET), 1982 (Box 2)
  - Positron for Synchrotron Light Source, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Positron Group, miscellaneous notes and discussions, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
  - Positron Group White Paper and notes, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Positron Microscope
    - Department of Energy, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Funding, 1984 (Box 2)
    - General description, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Patent, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Support from the University of Michigan, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Positron Polarization Grant Proposals, 1980-1985; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Positron Polarization Proposal and Technical Report, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Positronium Research Funding, 1976-1980 (Box 2)
  - Precision Measurement Grant, 1971-1976 (Box 2)
  - "Precision Positron Polarimetry-a New Technique in Weak Interaction Studies", 1978-1981 (Box 2)
  - Research Staff Allocations, 1985; undated (Box 2)
  - Simultaneous Multisample Scintillation Spectrometer (SMSS) Proposal, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
  - Superconducting Solenoid correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Superconducting Solenoid design, 1975 (Box 2)
  - "A Superconducting Solenoid for Electron g-2 and Related Experiments" Grant Proposal, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Superconducting Solenoid notes, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Superconducting Solenoid specifications, 1982 (Box 2)
  - "Survey of Techniques for Detecting Trace Elements in Biological Systems", 1970 (Box 2)
  - "Tests of Fundamental Aspects of the Weak Interaction" grant proposal, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - "Tests of Fundamental Aspects of the Weak Interaction" project summary and renewal request, 1985-1988; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Triplet Positronium Drawings, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Undergraduate Research Program, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Variable Helicity Positrons, grant proposals, 1977-1984 (Box 3)
  - Vatican Project (Electron Chirality) Drawings and Outlines, circa 1988 (Box 3)
- Course Materials
  Course Materials (2 linear ft.; 1963-1989) contain syllabi, lecture notes, exams, problem sets, term papers and students' course evaluations. The material is arranged by course number and ranges from introductory to graduate level coursework. The series serves to document how physics was taught to a generation of University of Michigan students, as well as documenting the incorporation of new discoveries and trends into the curriculum. The course evaluations, where available, provide a sense of students' response to both Rich and the course.
  - Class Register, 1986-1989 (Box 7)
    [closed until January 1, 2064 ]
  - College Course 320, Introduction to Environmental Studies, 1970 (Box 3)
  - General Physics-
    - 125/126/146 Exams, 1967-1979 (Box 3)
    - 125, 1970-1984; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 126/146, 1963-1967 (Box 3)
    - 126/146 Problems and Assignments, 1970 (Box 3)
    - 126 Lecture Notes, 1970 (Box 3)
    - 126, 1982-1988; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 145, 1963 (Box 3)
    - 146/154 Exams, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - 154 Course Evaluations, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Physics 242-General Physics III
    - Exams, 1978-1980; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Lecture Notes, circa 1980 (Box 3)
    - Problem Sets, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Syllabi and miscellaneous notes, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
  - Physics 402-Light
    - Evaluations and memo, 1971; 1975 (Box 3)
    - Exams and Problems, 1971; 1975 (Box 3)
    - Lecture Notes, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Problem Set Solutions, circa 1975 (Box 4)
  - Physics 405-Intermediate Electricity and Magnetism
    - Course Evaluations and Outlines, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - "Electrostatics" Course Notes by Rich, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Electrostatics Lectures, circa 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Exams, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Problems and Solutions, circa 1969 (Box 4)
  - Physics 438-Electromagnetic Radiation
    - Assignments, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
    - Course Evaluations, 1970; 1987 (Box 4)
    - Exams, 1968-1987 (Box 4)
    - Lecture Notes, 1970; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Lecture Notes, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Lecture Transparencies, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Organization and Syllabus, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Problem Sets, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Physics 465-Physics Seminar
    - Term Papers, 1984 (Box 7)
      [closed until January 1, 2059 ]
    - Term Papers, 1988 (Box 7)
      [closed until January 1, 2063 ]
    - Writing Course, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Physics 640/644-Low Temperature Physics/ Advanced Atomic Physics
    - Lectures, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Lectures on Positronium, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Positronium Notes, undated (Box 4)
    - Syllabus and Exam, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Physics 643-Advanced Atomic Physics
    - Lectures, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Planning and Syllabus, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Seminar Overviews, 1984; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Seminar Overviews, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Physics 668-Advanced Astrophysics
    - Lectures, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Lectures, 1970; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Syllabus and Reference Notes, 1970 (Box 5)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence (0.5 linear ft.; 1962-1989) documents the international scope of Rich's professional contacts, as well as the wide range of his interests within the field of physics. Rich's folder headings have been retained.
  - China correspondence, 1984-1988 (Box 5)
  - Chupp, Timothy, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Eldrup, Dr. Morten re: positronium, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Goldanskii and Kondepudi correspondence, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Hamm, R.N. Oak Ridge National Laboratory, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Kajcsos, Zsolt, 1982-1985 (Box 5)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1969-1988; 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Mamyrin, Professor B.A., 1972 (Box 5)
  - Mani, H.S., 1969-1974 (Box 5)
  - Optical Activity Correspondence, 1977-1982 (Box 5)
  - Picasso, Emilio, 1967-1969; 1987 (Box 5)
  - Professional correspondence, A-Z, 1962-1988; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Radicati, Luigi A., 1974-1987 (Box 5)
  - Ramsay, Norman F., 1970-1989 (Box 5)
  - Sabbatical in France (1973), correspondence, 1971-1976 (Box 5)
  - Scandinavian correspondence, 1976-1982 (Box 5)
  - Travel and Conference correspondence, 1966-1985 (Box 5)
- Publications
  Publications (0.25 linear ft.; 1968-1989) includes a chronological compilation of scholarly articles by Rich which were published in refereed scientific journals. The remainder of the series consists of correspondence with publishers and journal editors, reviews of Rich's article submissions, and reviews by Rich of other physicists' work.
  - Publications of Arthur Rich, compiled, 1994 (Box 5)
  - American Institute of Physics, Popular Versions of Papers, 1975-1977 (Box 5)
  - Article Review of Wichers and van Klinken, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - Article Reviews, 1976-1988 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence re: publications, 1970-1987 (Box 5)
  - Electrostatics, 1969 (Box 5)
    Physics 405 text by Rich
  - Encyclopedia of Physics, 1989 (Box 5)
  - McGraw Hill Encyclopedia of Science and Technology, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Nature [journal], 1984 (Box 5)
  - Origins of Life [journal], 1985 (Box 5)
  - Physical Review Letters [journal], 1970-1982 (Box 5)
  - Physics Today [journal] correspondence, 1968; 1988 (Box 5)
  - Review of Modern Physics [journal], 1972 (Box 5)
- Topical File
  Topical File (1.25 linear ft.; 1966-1989) includes memos, correspondence, lecture notes and transparencies. This material covers Rich's administrative duties within the Physics Department, and the logistics of administering research projects. The series also documents his lectures at other universities and participation in physics advisory committees and conferences.
  - Academic Affairs Committee, 1979-1981 (Box 5)
  - Advisory Committee on Financial Affairs, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - American Physical Society Topical Group, 1989 (Box 5)
  - American Physical Society Topical Group on Fundamental Constants and Precise Tests of Physical Laws, 1987-1989 (Box 5)
  - Anti-Ballistic Missiles [ABMs], 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - Astrophysics Colloquium Presentation, early, 1970s (Box 6)
  - Beckman Instruments, In, circa 1989 (Box 6)
  - Brookhaven Program Advisory Committee, 1985-1988 (Box 6)
  - Canada Superconductor Cryogenics Co., 1973-1977 (Box 6)
  - Cerro Tololo International Observatory, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - Classified Research Policy, 1985-1986 (Box 6)
  - Departmental Review, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Electron g-factor Drawings, circa 1970-1978 (Box 6)
  - Equipment Donations, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Europe Trip, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Gamma Ray Telescope (GARTAR) Drawings and Slides, circa 1970 (Box 6)
  - High Flux Beam Reactor (HFBR) Advisory Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
  - International Conference on Atomic Physics (ICAP) Workshops, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
  - International Society for the Study of the Origin of Life, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Invention and Disclosure, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Louisiana State University, 1976 (Box 6)
  - McGraw-Hill Observatory, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Society of Fellows, 1979-1983 (Box 6)
  - Muon (g-2) Experiments, 1979 (Box 6)
  - National Science Foundation Technical Review Subcommittee, 1979 (Box 6)
  - New York University and Yale University outline and transparencies, mid-1980s (Box 6)
  - Physics Department Centennial, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Physics Department Chair Search Committee, 1986-1987; 3 folders (Box 7)
    [closed until January 1, 2017 ]
  - Physics Department Committee on Long Range Problems, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Physics Department National Ranking, 1982-1984 (Box 6)
  - Physics Department Salaries, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
  - Precision Measurements Research Priorities, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Publicity and clippings, 1966-1988 (Box 6)
  - Qualifying Exams, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Renovations to Physics Lab Space, 1984-1989 (Box 6)
  - Sabbatical, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Sixth International Conference on Atomic Physics, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR), 1985-1986 (Box 6)
  - Solenoid Lecture Drawings, circa 1970s (Box 6)
  - Stanford Gyrorelativity Experiment, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Symposium on Diversity and Research, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Talk Outlines, undated; 1984-1989; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - William L. Williams Memorial Award, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - Williams, William L., 1986-1988 (Box 6)
- Photographs
  Photographs (2 folders; ca. 1974-1988) contains pictures of Rich in his laboratory with fellow researchers, and at Cerro-Tololo Observatory with colleague William L. Williams. There is also a photograph of an early positron microscope image.
  - Positron Microscope Image, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Rich with Students and Colleagues, circa 1970-1988 (Box 6)